José Emilio Pacheco Papers, circa 1940s-2010s: Finding Aid C1619
Manuscripts Division
- Correspondence, 1940-2010s; 10 boxes
  - Correspondence, circa 2010s; 2 folders (Box B-001298, Folder 4-5)
    Carpeta 4 - Cartas de: Mary Docter, José Antonio Zambrano, Julio Figueroa, Josué Ramírez, Daniel Baruc Espinal Rivera, Hernán Sánchez de Pinillos, Michael Collier, Luis Marina, Roberto Gil Zuarth, Javiel Lozano Alarcón, Consuelo Sáizar, Felipe Calderón Hinojosa, Gabriel Zaid, Juan José Guerrero Sanginés, Teresa Hernández-Vela Borja, María Cristina García Cepeda, Patricia Rosas Lopategui, Fausto Vega, Eduardo Matos, Adolfo Martínez Palomo, Luis Fernando Lara, Cristina Fuentes La Roche, Francisca Noguerol, Sergio Romero Salas, Efrén Rodríguez, Arturo Martínez Nateras, David Landeros, Arturo López Corella, Fernando del Paso, Raúl Ferraez, Susana Reyes, José Félix Zavala, Antonio Gálvez, José Ortiz Monasterio Prieto, Carmen Núñez, Odvidio Reyna, Armando Ponce, Vicente Quirarte, Francisco Javier Morán Hernández, Dolores Repetto, Víctor Rodríguez Núñez, Natalia Marcos Guillamas, Myrna Ortega, Rita Gabbai-Tazartès, Giōrgos Rouvalēs, Enrique Krauze, Lourdes Galaz, Rafael Olea Franco, Héctor Aguilar Cabrera, Rosa López, Carlos Campillo Serrano, Rosa Beltrán, Anna Krzywania.
    Carpeta 5 - Cartas de: Rubén Ochoa, José Sarukhán, Adolfo Martínez Palomo, Víctor García de la Concha, Jesús Oyamburu, Mariana Simón Chavero, Jesús Alejo Santiago, Inocencio Reyes Ruiz, Guillermo Schavelzon, Mite Stefoski, Roberto Carlos Pérez, Felipe Calderón Hinojosa, Alejandro Duque Amusco, Javier Garciadiego, Xavier Robles, Alonso Lujambio, Héctor Orestes Aguilar Cabrera, Enrique Torre López, Carmen Caffarel Serra, Samar Ezzat Abd el Azim, Manuel Marín.
  - Correspondence, undated; 4 folders (Box B-001299, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence: Family, circa 1960s-1990s; 1 folder (Box B-001299, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Octavio Paz, 1966-1977; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 1)
    Includes a black-and-white photograph depicting José Emilio Pacheco with Octavio Paz and Homero Aridjis in Spoleto, Italy (1967).
  - Correspondence: Carlos Fuentes, circa 1965-1968, 1984; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Juan Vicente Melo, 1959-1960, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: José Miguel Oviedo, circa 1968-1992; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Sergio Galindo, 1958-1961, 1963; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Bruno Arcudi, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 6)
- Printed Materials, 1940-2011; 3 boxes
  Consists of a variety of printed materials, including periodicals, newspaper clippings, articles, publications, broadsides, and other materials.
  - Printed material about Pacheco, circa 1970s-2011; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 7)
  - Periodical: Nivel, gaceta de cultura", 1961 April 25; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 8)
    Periodical includes various poems by Pacheco.
  - Periodical: Pájaro Cascabel", 1963 May; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 8a)
    Periodical contains the poem "Entre centro y ausencia," escrito por Pacheco.
  - Newspaper: A quemarropa: Ocupen su localidad, noches de poetas en la SN", 2008 July 18; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 9)
  - Periodical: Símbolo (UNAM), 1957; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 9a)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, circa 1960s-2000s; 2 folders (Box B-001300, Folder 10-11)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1960s-2000s; 1 folder (Box B-001300, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1940s-2000s; 3 folders (Box B-001301, Folder 1-3)
  - Poster: Homenaje a José Emilio Pacheco, 1993 April; 1 box (Box P-000119)
    Contains poster from "Tercer Encuentro de Escritores Mexicanos" with pencil drawing of Pacheco signed by H. [Carrizon], as well as signed inscriptions on the back, from presumably organizers of the event.
- Other Materials, 1950-2010s; 4 boxes
  This file group consists of photographs, chiefly depicting Pacheco with friends; biographical documents; certificates; royalties received by Pacheco; materials related to awards given to Pacheco, including speeches; texts of presentations and conversations; and other materials.
  - Photographs, 1980s-1990s; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001301, Folder 4)
    Includes chiefly photographs of José Emilio Pacheco with friends and attending lectures/talks. Other photographs include Cristina Pacheco with Marcela Lombardo (December 1993), and an unidentified photograph of possibly a family member. Most of the photographs are undated. Also included is an idenfication card with Pacheco´s photograph from I.N.A.H. (Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia).
  - Biographical materials, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001301, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum vitae, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001301, Folder 6)
  - Certificates, 1979, 1993, 1998, 2005; 1 folder (Box B-001301, Folder 7)
  - Faculty reviews, 1989-1990, 1997-2000; 1 folder (Box B-001301, Folder 8)
  - Ingresos de derechos de autor, circa 1960s-2000s; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 1)
  - Premio Cervantes, 2009-2010; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 2)
  - Palabras al recibir el Premio Alfonso Reyes, 2004 October 25; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 3)
  - Premio Reina Sofía, 2009; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 4)
  - Texto leído en el Palacio de la Moneda al recibir el Premio Iberoamericano de Literatura, 2004 May 14; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 5)
  - Struga Golden Wreath Award: "Unas palabras de agradecimiento", 2013; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 6)
  - Palabras al recibir el Premio Ciudad de Granada-Federico García Lorca, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 7)
  - Palabras de agradecimiento, homenaje de UAM (Universidad Autónoma Metropolitana), 2002 October; undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 8)
  - Palabras de agradecimiento: Medalla de Bellas Artes, 2009 June 28; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 9)
  - Agradecimiento a el Colegio de México, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 10)
  - Copies of various speeches given by Pacheco, circa 1990s-2000s; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 11)
  - "A 150 años de la Academia de Letrán: discurso de ingreso al Colegio Nacional", 1986 July 10; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 12)
  - Texto leído por Pacheco para darle la bienvenida a Eduardo Matos Moctezuma en el Colegio Nacional, 1993 June 24; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 13)
  - Discurso de la Universidad Autónoma de Campeche, 2010 March 3; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 14)
  - Presentación en Voz Viva por Pacheco: Salvador Novo, antología poética, 1960; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 15)
  - Presentación por Pacheco: Vicente Leñero, circa 1978; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 16)
  - Presentación por Pacheco de la "Iconografía de Jaime García Terrés", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 17)
  - Clippings and agenda related to: Homenaje Nacional a Enrique González Martínez, circa 1995; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 18)
  - Discurso de recepción a Mario Lavista en el Colegio Nacional, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 19)
  - Texto de la presentación por Pacheco en el Colegio Nacional: La Poesía de Alfonso Reyes, 2009 July 21; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 20)
  - Texto de entrevista con Pacheco: "El Premio Paz, la corona a las batallas en la escritura", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 21)
  - "Una conversación entre José Emilio Merino y José Emilio Pacheco", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001302, Folder 22)
  - "Diálogo entre José Emilio Pacheco y Jorge Aguilar Mora", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 1)
  - Una conversación entre Fernando Benítez y Pacheco: "Los espacios de la literatura", 1983 July 27; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 2)
  - "Gracias, José Emilio", por Rosaura Barahona, 1993; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 3)
  - Boletín informativo matutino, Heberto Padilla, 1971 April 28; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 4)
  - Conference: Association of Hispanics of Great Britain and Ireland, 1968; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 5)
  - Programa: "Entre libros", Rosario Castellanos, Juan Vicente Melo y José Emilio Pacheco, circa 1961-1962; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 6)
  - Departmental meeting minutes, 1967 November-1968 February; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography of periodicals/articles: José Emilio Pacheco, circa 1950s-1980s; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 8)
  - Departamento de Investigaciones Históricas, circa 1973-1976; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 9)
  - Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia, 1973, 1979; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 10)
  - Ayuntamiento de Granada, circa 2005; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 11)
  - Research materials: Río de la Piedad, circa 1970s-1980s; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 12)
  - Comunicación y Relaciones Públicas: 40 Festival Internacional Letras en San Luis, 2008 June; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 13)
  - Celebraciones y homenajes, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 14)
  - Audiocassette: José Emilio Pacheco, poesía y prosa (selección), voz del autor, 1992; 1 folder (Box B-001303, Folder 15)
    1 audiocassette. Lado A. Poemas; Lado B. Narrativa: Un capítulo de Las batallas en el desierto, y un capítulo de Moríras lejos.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    For preservation reasons, original analog and digital media may not be read or played back in the reading room. Users may visually inspect physical media, but may not remove it from its enclosure. All analog audiovisual media must be digitized to preservation-quality standards prior to use. Patrons may request digital copies of original analog media, but will be responsible for the cost of digital conversion, payable in advance. Turn-around time for such requests will depend on the size and scope of the project. Requests should be directed to Public Services staff.
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2010s; 4 folders (Box B-001304, Folder 1-4)